hi everyone it's cohort three
August 8th and we're in our first
discussion on chapter 10.
so before we look to the text or any of
the specific questions
um
would anyone like to just give any
comments or thoughts on Ted
hey Daniel I I'm pretty yeah I'm not
prepared for chapter 10 so it's better
I'm gonna actually means I I'll read uh
later
no sorry bye
um
well
chapter 10 has no
figures or equations it's it's a lot of
um synthesis and
overview
anyone want to give any comments or or
we can like look over it and try to pull
out some questions pull out some
thoughts
what do you think is the relevance of
this quotation in general we are least
aware of what our minds do best
is that true
I think we should first know what he
mean about the awareness
what is awareness
because the we just
suppose to this world but you know we
have so much different approach about
awareness about Consciousness about mind
some philosopher
they they don't accept this
assumption they they think this is a we
should just work with neuron and bearing
Network neuron synops and no extra vote
because the
nobody can exactly know what is
awareness
we have different
introduction about awareness
why would Minsky say this
it reminds me of the um
the the discussion of uh the transparent
and opaque mental processes
with transparent mental processes are
like air like you see through them which
is to say you can't see them
opaque you can see them by virtue of
them blocking the something of light
so it's kind of like the fish in the
water
doesn't know about the water and so the
processes that are transparent to us
the things that are the most routine the
most mundane
we have this at least quote is saying
we're going to have the least awareness
of these
I'm not fully sure because I'm I believe
there are certain things we are unaware
of that our minds do well
but also I believe there are things our
minds do well that we are aware of
so I don't know if the general claim can
be said that we're least aware
of what we do best
since I think there's things that we're
aware of or not that we do well or not
but it's kind of a side point but but
it's you know as with all these quotes
they just start the chapter with kind of
a fun provocative
declaration
all right well
chapter 10 is a really interesting
chapter
they wrap up active inferences main
theoretical points that's part one
chapters one through five
and the Practical implementations
chapter six to ten
then they connect the dots abstract away
from the specific active inference
models discussed in previous chapters to
focus on integrative aspects of the
framework
all right
this is another
another spicy
peace
spicy and contentious
does active inference provide a complete
solution to the Adaptive problems that
sentient organisms have to solve
foreign
at all of anything
I mean we can vote and decide
but but but
um
what would be another way to say it or
how how would people yeah SML please
yeah you asked amazing questions
this approach I mean actively Affairs
can't solve everything but the
if nobody know about a future but at
least this optimistic approach is so
better than religious we just suppose
[Music]
everything is like a mystery
with this with this Assumption return we
can order so much uh thing for research
and scientists and Physicians can
research about that but if we we think
everything is Mystery just we give
forbid people for researching and uh in
the end we can't we can't achieve
anything
so my Approach is optimistic about
not in the moment
this will be a long procedure in and
future is open
great
yeah
treating things as a mystery or
somewhere on the mystery continue on
there with some amount of uncertainty
then it plus action so let's let's
figure it out and then this is kind of
like do we think that we're on the path
to achieving
a solution
to the Adaptive problems that sentient
organisms have to solve
or is this going to be a fruitless path
I think we we're
um through our actions we're on the
optimistic path
but I think this is a really
um
I mean it's a bold claim
and the narrow interpretation is did the
textbook provide a complete solution
but that's a little too narrow and I
think the broader question as Mel that
you point to is like as a long term
fields
will we have a scope
of addressing adaptive problems that
sentient organisms have to solve I even
think about it
outside of sentient organisms
just to the Adaptive problems that
things have to solve
where some kinds of things are adaptive
sentient organisms but that's not all
kinds of things
and then also
but so that's that's big
um however the second part of the claim
um is a little bit uh clearer and I
think more supported
active inference therefore offers a
unified perspective on problems like or
phenomena like
perception action selection attention
and emotional regulation
which are usually treated in isolation
and Psychology and Neuroscience
so I think that is a super strong claim
that
um can be pointed to when people what
does it mean that it's a unifying theory
of perception cognition and action or
what what does it mean that that the
first principle's approach
it's like well if you go to a
neuroscience conference
you're going to see totally different
ontology narratives tools documents
philosophies
um
on even just like the visual system
perception action selection attention
the models that are developed for visual
perception select action selection and
attention
those models may have no
interoperability at all
now that's not to say that they can't be
part of an integrated fabric
of of a pluralistic scientific accounts
so it's not like it it doesn't matter if
they're not Unified
but this comes back to the needs and the
scruffies
do we want
um
coherence within and across systems of
Interest
or everybody has kind of like a level
with a tap out and just say no that's
like too much integration but at least
with these phenomena that they point to
here
the book
uh and the literature demonstrate that
these different phenomena
can be considered
in an integrated model
whereas approaches that don't start from
a first principle's position
in general do not have that ability
then they're going to connect to some
established Theory
and finally
extend into some broader topics
okay
wrapping up
only 190 pages
only only
95 page flips
away
95 little epistemic actions
uh
we're at the the end of the this little
chapter of the journey
the book offers a systematic account of
theoretical underpinnings and practical
implementations of active inference
uh on these pages
they summarize the chapters this is one
reason why I think it may be helpful to
have chapter 10 be read at the beginning
because they're going to summarize like
really clearly what each chapter does so
chapter one that's an overview
chapter 2 the low road that's the how
Bayesian statistics and the generative
modeling
chapter 3 is the high road the Y
self-organization and persistence far
from equilibrium modeled through the
Markov blanket
chapter four
gives formal details on active inference
focusing again on the generative model
and this time exploring it a little bit
more fully in the context of variational
inference
chapter five
gives three connected case studies from
mammalian neuroscience
and talks about how these different
neural systems
can be modeled with active inference and
then how once you model them separately
with active inference you can kind of
stitch them together really nicely
chapter six was the recipe for Designing
active inference models
a little bit of a Playbook or a
guidebook
that also brings up a lot of different
questions and considerations about
scientific modeling
chapter seven and eight
were respectively about discrete and
continuous time generative models
chapter 9
was about active inference in the
setting of model-based data analysis
giving a little bit of information about
how you'd go about
doing a database analysis why you might
do that and and what that looks like and
so in that way it's kind of like chapter
six about building the generative model
but chapter nine is gonna
pull back another level and look at
what do you do with data
thank you
10.3 connecting the dots
great damn it
so
then it decades ago
many decades ago
lamented
that cognitive scientists devote too
much effort to modeling isolated
subsystems
or even isolated phenomena so not even
just like oh the visual tract
but like
visual perception in this one setting
whose boundaries are often arbitrary or
even worse disciplinary
he suggested to try instead modeling the
whole iguana a complete cognitive
creature perhaps a simple one and an
environmental Niche for it to cope with
esmail
what do you think about that or what did
it reference
bring up for you
yeah
then it's always
[Music]
I mean he always is speaking about the
extra word
he first asked were you imagine for
example Consciousness after that you
make for yourself problem
philosophy zombie
I think all of you know what I mean
foreign philosophy zombie but uh he has
first
you should um you you should suggest we
have something name a Consciousness
after that we can speak uh philosophy
zombie doesn't have Consciousness and
everything like mind like awareness I
told you the first submitting
and we should just research about a
specific experience experimental
equation about mind about bearing and
even he denied a phenomenal and every
phenomenal uh concept
I think his idea is so close to
emergence
this thing you you
accounted like perception sensation
and so on all of them are a kind of
emergence I mean
the difference
compared with neuron and brain but
this is just bearing and neuron and not
exteriority and something V effects on
the world and Vault effect on us
something like this and we don't need
I'm angry with Dennis we don't need so
much extra
vote suppose and after that we will fall
in the problem
awesome yeah
pretty cool how a lot of those topics
like emergence and systems properties
which come from the Natural Sciences
then connect back to consciousness
and awareness like like we discussed a
little earlier
um
so benefits of active inference you know
next time you're at a party and you know
hanging out relaxing
one benefit of active inference is that
it offers a first principal account of
the ways in which organisms solve their
adoptive problems so even beyond the
theoretical Unity of diverse cognitive
phenomena like perception attention and
so on
a benefit of active inference is that it
gives a normative approach
so not just an is but actually an ought
and says this is how it should
be modeled
um I think it's it's it's easy to
um
be startled by a normative approach
because it can feel like impositional
or constraining
but I think that's part of our
interesting
Journey
is to understand what this normativity
is
and and
um what exactly is being what what ought
to be what way
and I'm sure there's many ways to say it
but but um
there's sort of some there's some some
narrow odds and some broader odds a
narrow ought would be like for solving a
statistical problem with variational
inference
variational free energy is the best that
you're going to do
so that's kind of that's like saying you
know if you're doing a linear regression
you ought to use the L2 sum of squares
Norm
um but but
there's also kind of this broader
potentially less formalized normative
stance
which is that one
ought to
extend from that narrow ought about
variational free energy as the
imperative for statistical modeling
and that you then
ought to model
specific cognitive processes perception
action attention and emotion
as well as their mechanistic
manifestations
in a unified way
now someone else could say well I have a
different normativity
I think that specific cognitive
processes should be modeled in different
and income measure it ways
I guess that could be someone's
normativity or somebody could say
I've never really thought about that I
don't I don't think I have a strong
prior
let alone a normative stance on whether
things like should or shouldn't be
integrated
but but again it's just an interesting
um topic and and how many times does
normative come up in the book
you know 30 times
that's um
that's more times than you'll see
normative outside of like a
deontological ethics
book
and here's what they explained right in
the very beginning
normative means there's some standard
against which behavior can be scored
this is that narrower sense
free energy they're saying ought to be
the right quantity
for perceptual modeling
but then there's this secondary odds
which is a little bit like
and so you ought to do things in a
unified way
but that's a little bit less formal
but here's here's that normative level
it's Central assumptions all processes
minimize variational free energy so it
goes kind of this narrow piece
for a given statistical problem vfe is
the best estimator
and then there's this like slightly
broader normativity which is and you
ought to use vfv
for everything
to the extent that they say that
[Music]
um
the problems that things face that
organisms or or other things face can be
described as inactive
they're they're related to action in the
world
so that's very compatible with embodied
inactive extended and cultured
Etc
affective neuroscience and pragmatism
and also
the preferences
are defined explicitly over
observations
this connects to perceptual control
theory
and also just
um
not historically
by tethering or modeling
to sensory data
that's kind of like
where the robber hits the road with not
overfitting
like
there's more that could be said there
but
by making sure that variational free
energy is a function of our beliefs and
the real incoming data
that's a a very strong check
on not overfitting not like proposing
some auxiliary variable
and then being super precise about the
auxiliary variable
but then the actual empirical data we
may be not modeling well
again more lists
of cognitive phenomena
pretty similar here they insert looks
like memory and intention
it's like
slowly mutating and expanding the list
of cognitive phenomena
what can organisms do they can change
their belief
perception learning attention
internal States
or they can change the world
action
change your mind change the world
two ways
to produce free energy
the third piece of the organism is the
sensory data but we keep our Thumb off
the scale
so the only two things that the organism
can do is change its mind and change the
world changing the world then changes
the external States
and that has indirect effect on sensory
data
they talk about memory
they talk about planning
planning and memory
can be understood as a
two sides of the same timeline
they have different in our just just in
our Arrow of time going forward world of
course memory is different than planning
because memory doesn't have the same
[Music]
um
causal impact on our action selection
but yet our memories can influence what
we do
so it's not that they're without causal
impact but in both cases whether it's
reaching into the past with memory or
reaching into the future with planning
we can consider that a deep temporal
model
and deep temporal models so so that
that's how you synthesize memory with
planning and situational awareness in
the moment deep temporal models
now we're going to bring in another
level of the synthesis which is well
what is that deep temporal model about
maybe that deep temporal model
says
it has something to do with
interoception and emotion
so just there in a few sentences
that is a synthesis of past present and
future
sensory exteroceptive sensory
interceptive and affective
so that's that's what they mean by
what's enabled
and these kinds of relationships might
be pointed to
in
another field of Neuroscience or in
other fields but if it came from
Neuroscience it's unlikely to transfer
to spaceships and computers and all
these other systems
and whether it did or didn't transfer it
would be kind of descriptive and elusive
but it wouldn't have a formal basis like
we know that active inference does
okay again they're just hammering the
point home
we don't start by defining cognitive
functions
and try to puzzle piece them together
we start by what they characterize as
the complete solution
or maybe we could modify the adjective
and the noun like a comprehensive
approach or a unified account
but we provide a complete solution to
the problems that organisms have to
solve and then analyze those Dynamics
or fine-tune those Dynamics
to develop properties
that remind us of cognitive functions
so like what this reminds me of is
um sequential Dynamics
so
this came up multiple times
so sequential Dynamics have been modeled
with the lock of ultera model
it's just a property of certain
dynamical systems it's it's not an
apriori atomic cognitive function
but then that becomes deployed in a
cognitive behavioral modeling setting
to sequential actions like writing
so writing isn't a some core canonical
function
but
properties from dynamical systems we can
um
connect to their cognitive
concordances
and all these are maps not territories
so you know maybe there is some module
in some system but but
that's not necessarily even the best way
to go about modeling it
this connects back to the whole iguana
as well as to for example JF cloutier's
work with robotics
which mechanisms permit a living
organism to perceive the world remember
it and plan
so once you really think about what
something needs to do and be
to persist amidst uncertainty
the whole iguana
then even if you have a very coarse
grained picture of the whole iguana like
it's not atom level you should hear you
know it moves um out of the sun when
it's too hot into the sun when it's too
too cold
that is getting closer
to an understanding of the mechanisms
that permit it to live
rather than infinite molecular
description
those certainly our our mechanisms but
but they're not
helping us understand from a cognitive
perspective what's happening
okay with the normative perspective
we can reapproach
analogies and trade-offs
that have been identified in in
different systems
so exploration and exploitation
this paper
um is it's actually a really nice one
Hills at all 2015 I believe has some
representations of explore and exploit
in body
and in mind
so like come up with 10 words you know
you could go red orange yellow green
blue purple like that's kind of like
exploiting colors
or you can have like a Divergent
thinking
and similarly foraging
um you could be exploiting one resource
or
um exploring across resources
understanding that in the context of of
active inference which we explored a
little bit in the epistemic
rat in the maze
but it helps us rethink that explore
exploit and how to model and approach it
so beyond the theoretical Unity
we also get a bridge of principled means
of understanding corresponding neural
computations
it offers a process theory that connects
cognitive processing to expected
neuronal Dynamics
so you'll notice in the SPM package
that
a lot of the simulations just as part of
the default outputs they include like
dopaminergic signaling
and so that doesn't you know dopamine
does multiple things even in the
mammalian brain does multiple things in
different organisms brains so
um it's not saying that's the one and
only trace of dopamine
however
we can connect
molecular
mechanisms
to statistical properties like surprise
okay
now they're going to explore
implications of active for psychological
functions as if we were sketching a
psychology textbook
so it's kind of like
within the body of this textbook there's
the germ
of another textbook
and they're going to highlight
similarities and differences
another reason why it may be relevant to
read chapter 10 early
10-4
predictive brains predictive Minds
predictive processing
we've talked about this a fair amount
but rather than a world view in which
sensory data come in
and are processed and then make their
way to their final internal
representation and then are used to
engage action a sort of feed forward
model of
perception and action
inactive inference inheriting from
predictive processing
we have an ongoing generative model
that
is generating predictions expectations
anticipations about sensory data
and about action
and then incoming sensory data
are able to be juxtaposed as they say to
validate their hypotheses predictive
coding
and there's some subtlety with what's
predictive coding what's predictive
processing and so on
and then at a slower time scale
you have the model updating essentially
its weights through learning
that imperative
is self-evidising
the best generative model is the one
that's least surprised by incoming
sensory data
that's the maximum model evidence
and so that is how this epistemic and
pragmatic
um dual imperative is Unified through
action and active inference
predictive processing
they write the term predictive
processing is used in a broader and less
constrained sense compared to active
inference
so again probably a lot of things you
could say like active inference is
predictive processing plus action
or
active inference is predictive
processing with action under the free
energy principle
but they're more alike than not
and predictive processing is the gateway
drug
I mean
um
okay
lots more debates and and topics on that
perception
our perception
is our generative model
of course we want to be careful with the
map in the territory but I always return
to vision
we don't pay attention to our isocate
we don't notice our blind spot literally
we fill it in and we have high
resolution color vision all around the
eye
even though the retina doesn't support
that
so for me cicades blind spot and
peripheral color vision
give absolutely tangible evidence
that our visual perception
is generated and fine-tuned
not received
and likewise for other sensory
modalities
that concept of perception as
subconscious or subliminal inference
is ancients
helmholtz and before
Bayesian brain again another very
closely Allied topic with active
inference after all we're talking about
brains sometimes and we're talking about
[Music]
um
Bayesian statistics
so how is active inference related to
Bayesian brain
well
Bayesian brain refers to a family of
approaches that are not necessarily
integrated and make different empirical
predictions it's kind of a broad family
it's not like one specific model
because he could also refer to a little
bit more of a realist flavor the brain
does Bayesian computation or a little
bit more of an instrumentalist flavor we
use Bayesian statistics to model the
brain
but in either and and also it can apply
at different levels of explanation
but broadly
active inference is a Bayesian brain
hypothesis but it's not just about
brains and it's a process Theory not a
hypothesis but yes it's Bayesian it
could be about the brain
but if you do Bayesian brain plus action
under the fep
I I believe you also compose active
inference
but active inference is more integrated
it's more normative
and it is better described as a process
Theory that's falsifiable but but that
is very closely aligned with a
hypothesis
they return to predictive coding
which was discovered as a video
compression
algorithm
and only brought into the neurosciences
most empirically in the late 90s
so it's only been 24 years
since
some of these things have even come onto
the scene
action
in active inference action processing is
analogous to perceptual processing
it's all part of the generative model
in chapter five
we explored how top-down descending set
points predictions
can then induce action
that's the equilibrium point hypothesis
there's another discussion of sensory
attenuation
there was a box on that earlier in the
book it's kind of like the opposite of
attention is attenuation you know
turning it up is like more attention
turning it down is like attenuating
um
and there was discussion around how
attenuation
[Music]
of our so attenuating our attention to
sensory input
creates like it opens up a space of the
possible
where then we can undertake an action
selection
and then lock in that precision and
that's exactly what happens with an eye
cicade that's why we don't perceive the
isocate
High attention fixed gaze
and then it's like
we push on the clutch or pull off the
gas whether you drive automatic or
manual
um move the eye it's not noticed it's
not attended to but of course it's still
getting photons
and then once it's fixed again we
redeploy the attention
and so that's why our phenomenology of
vision
is basically fixed fixed
without
um and maybe some pathologies maybe it's
there's nausea
if there's a failure of that kind of
attenuation it might be very
unsettling
in the isocate setting but in the bodily
motor setting this is where
um some people
um are challenged with beginning motion
so they can't step off the gas
so then there's sensory inputs like no
you're in a chair you should just stay
here
um or or inability to stop motion
um
idea motor these are kind of broad
conceptual theories that active
inference brings a lot of rigor to
but they basically relate to mind and
body
actions are selected on the basis of
their predicted consequences
cybernetics
tote
test operate test exit we've also
connected octave to UDA observe
orientiside Act
perceptual control theory we also have
requisite diversity and good regulator
theorem
um basically everything related to
cybernetics
active inference is going to be able to
handle
with this specific note that the
preferences are over perceptions
which kind of grounds higher levels of
the system
optimal control theory so the inbound
perceptual and learning side of active
inference the cybernetic entity that's
like signal processing and sense making
the outgoing dependency on the mark on
blanket is connected to control theory
um
here's some discussions about
control theory
importantly optimal motor control is
kind of aligned with reward learning
in that there's a cost or a value
function it uses these economic
metaphors
cost value reward utility
whereas
we use all the apparatus that we've
described earlier we don't need to
invoke these economic metaphors or
[Music]
um
anything
but we can account for utility in
decision making
here's the economic theories of utility
maximization and reinforcement learning
we can account for those
with pragmatic value
dynamic programming there's really cool
modeling work that's using dynamic
programming in active inference
when when all people have is pragmatic
value utility reward
then
they have to propose these ad hoc
strategies
to get non-pragmatic Behavior
or to escape local Optima
like burn-in novelty bonus intrinsic
reward
the list goes on
active inference we just specify it up
front expected free energy epistemic
plus pragmatic value
rather than trying to find the most
rewarding or the highest utility path
we try to find the most likely path
so instead of climbing to the mountain
top of the mountain who knows if we're
at the top of the mountain
we're taking the path of least action
and that's what connects all of these
discussions to Bayesian mechanics
that's what makes it physics based among
other things
is that it's a variational principle of
least action
for cognitive systems
so just like a baseball with certain
starting conditions and so on has a
certain Parabola that's the path of
least action
the Bayesian updating with a given prior
and attention and incoming data stream
is going to update a certain way
on the path of least action now that
that path of least action may also be
described by the most rewarding
trajectory or the highest utility
trajectory or whatever
but it turns out that it's a lot more
General and generic to describe it as
taking a path of least action which is
something that physical systems do
rather than this kind of like
aspirational
highest utility approach
that's connected to decision making
there's no utility or cost function
inactive inference
we select action plans based upon their
probability
um
of happening
not based upon their probability of
providing a reward
and there's parameters like the shaky
hand parameter or the temperature on
decision making if you turn the
temperature to absolute zero
then you're going to select the action
that you think is better even if it's
only a little bit better
whereas if you have the shaky hand
parameter very high high temperature
decision making then you blur
differences in the expected free energy
of policies and you basically select the
policies at um
reinforcement learning
policy is used differently
model based and model 3rl
and policy gradient methods
which are similar
procedurally in certain ways to active
inference
however the objective function is
different
it's a reward function that's being
reforced reinforced it's not a
um
generative model
surprise bounding free energy explicitly
and there are some differences more
planning
behavior-bounded rationality
this kind of connects to type 1 type 2
thinking
deliberative dual Theory
rational economon
free energy theory of bounded
rationality
valence emotion motivation
now they're kind of exploring
broader phenomena
homeostasis allostasis enteroceptive
processing
pretty cool that active inference is
very flexible
to describe visual input or
um
pockets coming over the network
or interception
again needs and scruffies the neat wants
to have a unifying model that can
describe all those input output systems
or measurement control systems
the scruffy says no interception's
different than vision and that's
different than the computer packet
attention salience epistemic Dynamics
attention is covert action it's internal
action and it's modeled as such
overt action is embodied action
we can operationally Define attention as
the Precision associated with sensory
input if you're not paying attention
the sensory input doesn't matter in the
sense that it doesn't update your model
in the limit of paying extreme attention
whatever data point comes in you will
update your beliefs to be that
that's related to gain control in the
Bayesian setting like in audio
engineering
salience is expected Information Gain
salience is in terms of an action or
policy while attention is an attribute
of beliefs about sensory input
rule learning causal inference fast
generalization
great quote by Rumi
these are like half page to one page
long but there's you know there's
there's so much here and then active and
other fields open directions
sociocultural Dynamics we're exploring
that a lot in the ongoing course active
inference for the social sciences
machine learning and Robotics
huge topic a lot of work in this field
are those the only two
yeah
in summary
ending with with the Tolkien Lord of the
Rings quote
alluding to the golden ring on the cover
of the textbook
we are now at the end of our journey
their aim was to offer an introduction
to those interested in using methods
conceptually and formally
did they do it
however it is important to emphasize
active inference is not something that
can be learned purely in theory
we encourage anyone who has enjoyed this
book to think about pursuing it in
practice
whether or not you pursue a
computational practice
we hope you will reflect on it as you
engage in active inference and
day-to-day life
you might be looking
to see something you're not sure what it
is
it might be eating what you know you
like you might be trying something new
might be turning down the shower heat if
it's too hot might be
not turning down the shower Heat
ultimately we are confident that you
will continue to pursue active inference
in some form
that's the book
and then there's the appendices
any kind of closing thoughts
foreign
chapter
textual tap chapter no figures no
equations
it's all it's like a whole undergrad
degree kind of compressed
so
it covers a lot
I guess uh next week
we can uh
return to some of these
discussions bring up some of these notes
into the questions ask new questions
cool
any last comments
all right
thank you all see you next time
thank you very much bye